{"tossups": [{"question": "Members of this religious sect built the Round Stone Barn and helped develop Babbitt metal. Hannah Cohoon, a member of this sect, created many drawings of trees called \u201cgift drawings.\u201d This sect made property a \u201cconsecrated whole\u201d under leader Joseph Meachem and Lucy Wright. This group, which underwent a revival in Watervliet named the Era of Manifestations, initially settled in New Lebanon, New York. Mother Ann Lee helped lead this religious sect, and another of its members, Elder Joseph Brackett wrote the song<em> Simple Gifts</em>. For ten points, name this American religious sect named for their ecstatic dancing during worship.", "answer": "<b> Shaker</b>s (accept<b> United Society of Believers in Christ\u2019s Second Appearing</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Along with Emanuel Celler, a person with this surname sponsored the 1946 act that allowed Indian and Filipino immigration to the U.S. In a 1941 editorial, a man with this surname argued that the U.S. should replace Britain as the world\u2019s superpower in his article \u201cThe American Century.\u201d A woman with this married surname became the first female Ambassador to Italy in 1953; her husband founded<em> Sports</em> <em>Illustrated</em> and<em> Fortune</em>. For ten points, give this surname of socialite Clare Booth and<em> Life</em> publisher Henry.", "answer": "<b> Luce</b> (accept Henry<b> Luce</b> or Clare Booth<b> Luce</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This event names a legal test that requires that preemptive self-defense be \u201cinstant\u201d with \u201cno moment for deliberation.\u201d In response to this event, \u201cPirate Bill\u201d Johnston led a vigilante attack on the<em> Sir Robert</em> <em>Peel</em>, prompting the intervention of Winfield Scott on the orders of Martin van Buren. Amos Durfee was killed in this event which was preceded by Navy Island being declared the \u201cRepublic of Canada\u201d by William Lyon Mackenzie. For ten points, name this 1837 incident in which British soldiers burned a rebel ship and sent it over Niagara Falls.", "answer": "<b> Caroline</b> Affair", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This character, dressed in a pith helmet and safari clothing, interrogates Major Marchand at Fashoda in one cartoon from Punch. In another cartoon, this character impales a general as he tries to make a\u201cjump\u201d from ambition, power, and Calais to Dover as a satire of the Napoleonic Wars. This character, who was initially created by John Arbuthnot, asks \u201cWho\u2019s absent? Is it you?\u201d in a recruiting poster for World War I; in that representation, he wears a waistcoat with the pattern of the Union Jack on it. For ten points, name this national caricature of England.", "answer": "<b> John Bull</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "A<em> Blue Book</em> published by this family was America\u2019s first mail-order catalog. Favrile glass was developed by this family, which ran a company under businessman Charles Lewis and his son, designer Louis Comfort. For ten points, name this American family whose company designed ornate stained glass windows.", "answer": "<b> Tiffany</b> family (accept Humphrey<b> Tiffany</b>; accept Charles Lewis<b> Tiffany</b>; accept Louis Comfort<b> Tiffany</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A minister of this man, Joachim Fredrich von Blumenthal, negotiated the Peace of Oliva and created a system to allow for the creation of a permanent standing army. With Charles X Gustav, this man beat John II Casimir at the Battle of Warsaw. This Hohenzollern leader fought Sweden successfully at the Battle of Fehrbellin and during the \u201cGreat Sleigh Drive.\u201d The Duchy of Cleves was opened by this ruler for \u201cFrench Protestant comrades in Belief.\u201d Huguenots were invited to this man\u2019s land via the Edict of Potsdam. The Prussian army\u2019s reputation greatly improved under, for ten points, what 17th century\u201cGreat Elector\u201d of Brandenburg?", "answer": "<b> Frederick William</b> the Great Elector of Brandenburg <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Shortly before this event, the National Strike Council was established to coordinate political protests. Elena Poniatowski described eyewitness accounts of this event in her book<em> The Night of</em> [this event]. A 2001 report confirmed that nearby snipers were ordered to fire into the crowd during this event. Ernesto Soto led the Olympia Brigade during this event, in which several hundred people were killed in the Square of the Three Cultures. For ten points, name this massacre of students that took place in a namesake Mexico City neighborhood ten days before the 1968 Summer Olympics opened.", "answer": "<b> Tlatelolco</b> Massacre (prompt on Mexico City (student) massacre and other descriptions)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An observer group to oversee the withdrawal of an army from this region was established in United Nations Security Council resolution 915. At an ad hoc conference held by the OAU regarding possession of this territory, one nation claimed that President Tombalbaye conceded it. Land Cruisers were used in this uranium-rich region during an offensive that expelled a bordering nation\u2019s army from this region during the Toyota War. For ten points, name this historically disputed strip of land that runs roughly 100 kilometers between Chad and Libya.", "answer": "<b> Aouzou Strip</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Samuel Scott wrote about the \u201cTransformation of the French Army in an Age of Revolution\u201d from the Battle of Yorktown to this battle. This battle marked a \u201cnew era in the history of the world\u201d according to the author Goethe, who fought in it. A ridge containing a windmill is where the forces of Fran\u00b8cois Kellerman were stationed at the start of this battle, at which the Prussians called off several failed charges. Two days after this battle, France became a republic. For ten points, name this first major battle of the War of the First Coalition fought in a French village east of Paris.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Valmy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Americans supported Jos\u00b4e Manuel Balmaceda in a civil war in, for ten points, what South American country where an international incident arose from a brawl in Valparaiso?", "answer": "<b> Chile</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The speaker of a poem by this author meets \u201cSeven blood-hounds\u201d following \u201cMurder,\u201d who \u201chad a mask like Castlereagh.\u201d This author urged the people to \u201cRise like Lions after slumber / In unvanquishable number\u201d in poem written in the wake of the Peterloo Massacre. The speaker of a poem by this author of \u201cThe Masque of Anarchy\u201d meets a \u201ctraveller from an antique land\u201d who tells him of a statue whose pedestal reads \u201cLook on my Works, ye Mighty, and despair!\u201d A statue of Ramesses II inspired, for ten points, what British poet to write \u201cOzymandias?\u201d", "answer": "<b> P</b>ercy Bysshe<b> Shelley</b> (prompt on Shelley)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "After a leader of this party was exiled, his wife proclaimed herself a \u201cmother to all those who came out to face bullets for the sake of freedom\u201d from the steps of her home, which became known as \u201cthe house of the Umma.\u201d The leader of this party was exiled with Mostafa el-Nahas to the Seychelles in 1921. This party, which led a 1919 revolution against the government of Reginald Wingate, was founded by a follower of Ahmen Orabi, Saad Zaghloul. This party lost popularity after it cooperated with the British in opposing King Farouk, and was banned with all other political parties by Nasser in 1953. For ten points, name this party that called for a constitutional monarchy in Egypt.", "answer": "<b> Wafd</b> Party (accept<b> Delegation</b> Party; do not accept New Wafd Party)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Earlier, this man carried out the Duke of Alba\u2019s order to arrest the Count of Egmont, whose execution sparked the Eighty Years War in the first place.", "answer": "Sancho d\u2019<b>Avila</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The wife of a central figure in this scandal hung herself in West Palm Beach a week after condemning her husband\u2019s actions in a<em> 20/20</em> interview. Richard Kelly tried to avoid prison time by claiming he was only involved in this scandal because he was investigating it himself. A senator involved in this scandal expected to receive a stake in a titanium mining company by way of his lawyer, Alexander Feinberg. Angelo Errichetti, the mayor of Camden, New Jersey, was among those convicted in this scandal for accepting money for casino development from fictitious Arab sheikhs. For ten points, name this FBI sting operation in which seven Congressmen accepted bribes in the early 1980s.", "answer": "<b> Abscam</b> (accept<b> Abdul Scam</b>; accept<b> Arab Scam</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A musician from this country wrote a third symphony titled</b><em><b> Song of the Night</b></em><b> and an opera about the title Sicilian monarch,</b><em><b> King Roger</b></em><b>. A pianist from this country composed the opera</b><em><b> Manru</b></em><b> and spent ten months as its Prime Minister, during which time he</b> <b>signed the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Versailles. The Opus 10 of another pianist from this country is</b> <b>Versailles. The Opus 10 of another pianist from this country is</b> <b>a set of \u00b4etudes, the last of which was dedicated to (*)</b> <b>a set of \u00b4etudes, the last of which was dedicated to (*)</b> Franz Liszt and was inspired by the failure of the November Uprising. Karol Szymanowski [shi-man-ov-skee], Ignacy Paderewski [ig-NAT-zee pa-der-EHV-skee], and the composer of the<em> Revolutionary</em>\u00b4Etude are pianists from, for ten points, what homeland of Frederic Chopin [sho-pahn]?", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Katip Suma led members of this civilization on a jihad. Minh Mang conquered the rest of this civilization, forcing its people to eat lizard, pig, and cow meat because they were</b> <b>Muslim and Hindu. These people, who believed they were descended from (+)</b> <b>Lady Po</b> <b>Nagar, used lingam as symbols for Shiva. Hoi An was a commercial capital for this empire, and (*) </b> My Son [mee sohn] was one of its religious centers. Indrapura and Vijaya were capitals of, for ten points, what civilization once ruled by Bhadravarman and ultimately annexed by the Nguyen Dynasty, located in Southern Vietnam?", "answer": "<b> Champa</b> (civilization, people, kingdom, etc.)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The overthrow of this ruler was engineered by the Group of 184, led by Andre Apaid. Maxine Waters accused the US of orchestrating the overthrow of this ruler, who was originally supported by the Cannibal Army before they captured Gona\u00a8\u0131ves [gohn-ah-eev].</b> <b>This man, who was overthrown by (+)</b> <b>Raoul Cedras, was restored to power by 1994\u2019s</b> <b>Operation Uphold Democracy. This liberation theology priest was targeted at the St. Jean Bosco Massacre by the (*) </b> Tonton Macoutes [mah-coot] after criticizing Jean-Claude Duvalier [doo-vahl-yay]. A 2004 Guy Philippe-led coup overthrew, for ten points, what two time President of Haiti?", "answer": "Jean Baptiste<b> Aristide</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>De Witt Clinton approved of an endless chain this man invented to pull boats on the Erie Canal. Patents owned by this man relating to gelatin were named by his wife as \u201cJell-O.\u201dAt age 85, this man ran with Samuel Fenton Cary for president. At the Canton Iron Works, this man built the (+)</b><em><b> Tom Thumb</b></em><b> steam locomotive for the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad. Abram Hewitt helped this man found an institution that offered (*)</b> free tuition to all students until 2014. For ten points, name this man who ran in the 1876 Presidential Election with the Greenback Party, the namesake of a \u201cUnion\u201d school in New York City.", "answer": "Peter<b> Cooper</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Two members of this family were teachers in the Raritan Bay union, which was run by a man who married into this family. A member of this family responded to attacks from Congregationalists by writing \u201cLetters on the (+) Equality of the Sexes.\u201d Members of this family wrote the tract \u201cAppeal to the Christian Women of the South\u201d and edited</b><em><b> American </b><b>Slavery as It Is: Testimony of a Thousand Witnesses</b></em><b>. Two members of this family had a lecture series in (*) </b> Boston, and one of them married Theodore Weld. For ten points, name this Southern family whose members Angelina and Sarah called for abolitionism and women\u2019s rights?", "answer": "<b> Grimk\u00b4e</b> sisters", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}